Scott P. White

Data Scientist, Chemical Engineer, Entrepreneur

Lafayette, IN (Temporary) • Cell: (612)-756-6018 • spwhite1337@gmail.com

www.scottpwhite.com • GitHub.com/spwhite1337 • LinkedIn/In/Scott-P-White

Overview:

Chemical Engineering Ph.D., Start-Up Founder, and burgeoning Data Scientist. Extensive experience (~6 years) programming custom test scripts and analyzing the large, complex data sets that result in the context of analytical chemistry (Python, R, MATLAB). Successfully led a data-intensive engineering project from inception (Academia) to commercial implementation (Start-up). Very motivated to learn and expand my interdisciplinary background for the duration of my career.

Education

University of Minnesota - Twin Cities

Minneapolis, MN

Ph.D. in Chemical Engineering, NSF Fellow (GPA: 3.8)

Dec 2017

Thesis: "Label-Free, Microfluidic Biosensors with Printed, Floating-Gate Transistors" Advisors: Prof. C. Daniel Frisbie and Prof. Kevin D. Dorfman

University of Iowa

Iowa City, IA

B.S.E. in Chemical Engineering, Highest Honors (GPA: 4.0)

May 2012

Thesis: "Microstructured Photopolymers for Directed Spiral Ganglion Neurite Growth"

Advisor: Prof. C. Allan Guymon

Select Awards

National Science Foundation I-Corps Entrepreneurial Lead	July. 2017 - Sep. 2017
National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship	Aug. 2013 – Aug. 2016
Best Oral Presentation at MRS – Organic Bioelectronic	November 2015
UMN College of Science and Engineering Fellowship	Aug. 2012 – Aug. 2013
Student Speaker at 2012 University of Iowa Engineering Gradua	tion May 2012
Tau Beta Pi Dept. of Chemical Engineering Outstanding Senior	May 2012

Entrepreneurship

Printed Bioelectronic Solutions (UMN Tech Start-up) Founder

Minneapolis, MN Fall 2016 – Spring 2018

- Developed an electronic biosensing technology from a laboratory platform to an attractive prototype for adoption into regulated analytical protocols in food safety.
- Executed an intellectual property search to protect the technology and partnered with lawyers to draft the patent and identify the key differentiators from >40 IP samples.
- Completed the National Science Foundation's I-Corps program as an Entrepreneurial Lead by implementing LEAN startup fundamentals and market discovery procedures.
- Utilized data story-telling to gain customer insights (>100 interviews), recruit support from veteran entrepreneurs, and earn credibility with industrial partners.
- Led the project from inception to implementation as an entrepreneur. Successfully transitioned the technology from academia to the commercial space in <2 years.

Experience

Insight Data Science
Data Science Fellow with Insight Data Science

Remote Session

Fall 2018

- Built an application, Prescription Drugs: What's the Worst that Could Happen?, to supplement health apps (e.g. WebMD) by providing likelihood estimates of adversity.
- Analyzed >20 GB of public health records to connect the profile of a user to the seriousness of their outcome by maximizing precision (~0.90) across various ML models.
 - Utilized Scikit-Learn for Random Forest, Logistic Regression, Naive Bayes, and K-Means.
- Provided actionable recommendations to assuage a user's irrational health concerns.

University of Minnesota – Twin Cities
Post-Doc and Ph.D. Student, Chemical Engineering

Minneapolis, MN Aug. 2012 – Apr. 2018

Data Science

- Programmed electronic equipment to generate and implement user-friendly testing protocols and visualize the resulting data along with rudimentary analysis (LabView).
- Extracted complex signal waveforms from noise, designed and identified key signal features, and correlated markers with nano-scale properties using Python, MATLAB, R.
- Developed a website (<u>www.scottpwhite.com</u>) to highlight projects in Forecasting,
 Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Statistical Inference, and more.

Engineering R&D

- Invented a patented technique for electronic transduction of interfacial molecular capture by combining printed electronics with microfluidics
- Mapped operating regimes of floating gate transistors with electrolytes to connect fundamentals of semiconductor physics and electronics with biophysics
- Designed and manufactured a microfluidic circuit for efficient and facile delivery of samples to the sensor via photolithography and a plethora of cleanroom methods
- Communicated the work via publications, presentations (local and international), proposals, and mentoring of undergraduate/graduate students, and visiting scientists
- Developed expertise in Printed Electronics, Microfluidics, Polymer Processing, Data Analysis, Metrology, Biosensors, and Photolithography.

NASA Glenn Research Center Undergraduate Research Intern Cleveland, OH Fall 2011

- Synthesized alumino-silicate polymers and derivatives to optimize their mechanical and thermal insulating properties over a variety of temperature ranges
- Fabricated composite aerogel and inorganic materials for integration into a novel, high temperature laser heating apparatus
- Collaborated with a team of technicians to catalog the material properties of novel composite materials for heat protection applications.

Process Engineering Intern

- Collaborated with operators to optimize a new process off-gas safety feature
- Facilitated the shut-down, turn-around, and production of selective herbicides such as acetochlor, butachlor, and glyphosate

University of Iowa

Iowa City, IA

Undergraduate Research Assistant, Chemical Engineering

Jan. 2011 – Aug. 2012

- Developed a process to control the reaction-transport phenomena of biocompatible photopolymers to create tunable surface microstructures
- Collaborated with the Otolaryngology Department to interface the designed photopolymers with genetically engineering spiral ganglion neurites to identify genetic factors related to cellular growth and agglomeration

Patent

Electrolyte-Gated Transistors for Detection of Molecules White, S.P.; Dorfman, K.D.; Frisbie, C.D. Application No. PCT/US2015/045108 (pending)

Publications

- 10.) Detection and Sourcing of Gluten with Multiple Floating Gate Transistor Biosensors. **White, S.P.**, Frisbie, C.D., Dorfman, K.D. ACS Sensors 3.2 (2018): 395-402.
- Interfacial Charge Contributions to Chemical Sensing by Electrolyte-Gated Transistors with Floating Gates.
 Thomas, M.S., White, S.P., Dorfman, K.D., Frisbie, C.D. J. Phys. Chem. Lett. 9.6 (2018): 1335-1339.
- 8.) Rapid, Selective, Label-Free Aptameric Capture and Detection of Ricin in Potable Liquids using a Printed Floating Gate Transistor.

 White, S.P., Sreevatsan, S., Dorfman, K.D., and Frisbie, C.D. ACS Sensors 1.10 (2016): 1213-1216. ACS Author's Choice
- Operating and Sensing Mechanism of Electrolyte-Gated Transistors with Floating Gates: Building a Platform for Amplified Biodetection.
 White, S.P., Dorfman, K.D., and Frisbie, C.D. J. Phys. Chem C. 120.1 (2016): 108-117.
- Synergistic Increase in Ionic Conductivity and Modulus of Triblock Copolymer Ion Gels.
 Tang, B., White, S.P., Frisbie, C.D., and Lodge, T.P. Macromolecules 48.14 (2015): 4942-4950.
- 5.) Label-Free DNA Sensing Platform with Low-Voltage Electrolyte-Gated Transistors. White, S.P., Dorfman, K.D., and Frisbie, C.D. Analytical chemistry 87.3 (2015): 1861-1866.

- 4.) Neural Pathfinding on Uni-and Multidirectional Photopolymerized Micropatterns. Tuft, B.W., Xu, L., White, S.P., Seline, A. E., Erwood, A.M., Hansen, M.R., and Guymon, C.A. ACS applied materials & interfaces 6.14 (2014): 11265-11276.
- Effects of Olefin Content and Alkyl Chain Placement on Optoelectronic and Morphological Properties in Poly(thienylene vinylenes).
 Speros, J.C., Martinez, H., Paulsen, B.D., White, S.P., Bonifas, A.D., Goff, P.C., Frisbie, C.D., and Hillmyer, M.A. Macromolecules 46.13 (2013): 5184-5194.
- Photopolymerized Microfeatures for Directed Spiral Ganglion Neurite and Schwann Cell Growth.
 Tuft, B.W., Li, S., Xu, L., Clarke, J.C., White, S.P., Guymon, B.A., Perez, K.X., Hansen, M.R., and Guymon, C.A. Biomaterials 34.1 (2013): 42-54.
- 1.) An ADMET Route to Low-Band-Gap Poly(3-hexadecylthienylene vinylene): a Systematic Study of Molecular Weight on Photovoltaic Performance. Speros, J.C., Paulsen, B.D., White, S.P., Wu, Y., Jackson, E.A., Slowinski, B.S., Frisbie, C.D., and Hillmyer, M.A. Macromolecules 45.5 (2012): 2190-2199.

Presentations

- 7.) **White, S.P.**, Dorfman, K.D., Frisbie, C.D., "Food Sensors with Printed, Floating-Gate Transistors." *North American Chemical Residue Workshop (NACRW)*, Summer 2018, Naples, FL
- 6.) **White, S.P.**, Thomas, M., Dorfman, K.D., Frisbie, C.D., "Biosensors Utilizing Printed Floating Gate Transistors (FGTs) and Microfluidics." *IPRIME Annual Meeting*, Spring 2017, Minneapolis, MN
- 5.) **White, S.P.**, Sreevatsan, S., Dorfman, K.D., Frisbie, C.D., "Rapid Quantitation of Toxic Protein Levels by Combining Printed Electronics and Microfluidics." *AIChE Annual Meeting: Biosensor Devices: Platforms and Techniques.* Fall 2016, San Francisco, CA.
- 4.) **White, S.P.**, K.D. Dorfman, C.D. Frisbie, "Operating Mechanism of Biosensors Utilizing Floating-Gate Transistors and Electrolyte Dielectrics." *MRS Biannual Meeting: Organic Bioelectronics From Biosensing Platforms to Implantable Nanodevices*. Fall 2015, Boston, MA
- 3.) **White, S.P.**, K.D. Dorfman, C.D. Frisbie, "Biosensing Mechanism of Floating-Gate Transistors Utilizing Electrolyte Dielectrics." *AIChE Annual Meeting: Biosensor Devices: Platforms and Techniques.* Fall 2015, Salt Lake City, UT
- 2.) **White, S.P.**, K.D. Dorfman, C.D. Frisbie, "Label-Free Biosensing with Printed, Low-Voltage Electrolyte-Gated Transistors" *IPRIME Annual Meeting*, Spring 2015, Minneapolis, MN

1.) **White, S.P.**, K.D. Dorfman, C.D. Frisbie, "Printed, Electrolyte-Gated Transistors as Label-Free Biosensors." *AIChE Annual Meeeting: Biosensor Devices: Platforms and Techniques*. Fall 2014, Atlanta, GA

Teaching Experience

University of Minnesota – Twin Cities Ph.D. Student, Chemical Engineering

Minneapolis, MN August 2012 – May 2017

- Teaching Assistant
 - Diffusion, Junior Chemical Engineers
 - Reactor Design, Junior Chemical Engineers
 - Unit Operations Laboratory, Junior Chemical Engineers
- Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Mentor
 - Four students total from a variety of demographic, scholastic, and geographic backgrounds

University of Iowa Undergraduate Engineering Student Iowa City, IA Spring 2010 – Spring 2012

- Teaching Assistant
 - Chemical Process Design, Senior Chemical Engineers
 - Chemical Process Safety, Junior Chemical Engineers
 - Process Calculations, Sophomore Chemical Engineers
 - Engineering Flow and Heat Exchange, Sophomore Chemical Engineers